So what does your split look like now?
>> So the split I follow now is essentially
the same one I've always followed and it
is and I want to be clear why I'm saying
Monday or Tuesday because there needs to
be flexibility in one schedule too. This
is important. So Monday or Tuesday I
train my legs.
>> Mhm.
>> Calves, hamstrings, quads, maybe some
direct like glute training but probably
not. Couple warm-ups, two to three
maybe, but usually just two hard sets to
failure. If I have a training partner,
there may be some assisted reps. So
quads would be two working sets of leg
extensions. I'll leave out the warm-ups.
Two to three cuz I'm need a bit more
there. Lying hamstring curls to failure.
Then belt squat. My favorite movement. I
actually bought a belt squat machine
because you don't have to load the
shoulders.
>> Which one do you like?
>> I use the pitch shark. And Rogue's got
now one that's kind of more of a
fan-based one. And there are a bunch of
It's a lot of fun to go on Instagram and
some of the the gym equipment assessment
accounts as a whole world. Sorinx has
one. There are all sorts of great ones
out there. I bought the Pitch Shark.
>> I'll reinforce the belt squat.
>> Love the belt squat. It takes a little
bit getting used to because some people
feel as if, you know, it's like jamming
into their hips or something. You can
put a towel there if you need to. I
mean, all the Westside barbell guys
would talk about belt squat. They would
load it up. You can actually march with
it to build build all sorts of
stabilizing muscles. I mean, that's an
incredible cardio workout. You just put
a couple plates on each side and you and
you just march lifting your knees and
like after like a minute you're like
this is this is no way I can continue
this a great workout. But I end up doing
leg extensions, leg curls, then belt
squat and then I may throw in a couple
work sets of hack squat and that's it.
And that's Monday or Tuesday. The day
after legs is always a rest day. Like if
you train legs properly, the next day
should be a rest day. You should need
it. Ideally, I would do sauna and cold
that day. These days I haven't had time.
A day later, I pick. Systemically, you
have to ask yourself, am I systemically
exhausted? My did my nervous system take
enough of an ass beating on that Monday
or Tuesday that I need two days off
after legs? And if it was very, very
intense, then I'll do some sort of 20 or
30 minute cardio. Typically, it's a run,
not an allout run, not a jog, just
somewhere in between. Probably in the
zone, let's just call it zone 3ish, zone
3, four. Okay? So you're not sucking for
air, but it's not a sprint workout. It's
not zone two. And then I'll do a push
pull. I'll do a chest and back workout.
And neck.
>> What do you use for neck?
>> I have a 4-way neck machine.
>> You do? I do.
>> Which brand do you use?
>> Hammer strength.
>> Hammer strength. Yeah. And again, the
reason I'm asking this guys is not to
plug particular manufacturers because
the physics and the geometry and so on
really matters. It really matters.
>> Especially in my experience with
something that has injury potential. I
have a four-way neck machine also. Oh,
cool.
>> I do it very very slowly myself. Like
don't overdo it. If you've never trained
neck, do not rush into like high
velocity stuff, but that's why I was
asking it.
>> Neck is very important. I'll talk about
specifically what I'll do if I don't
have access to that. Some people be like
chest and back same day and rear delts.
And yeah, I think of it as like a torso
workout.
>> Mhm.
>> Because I'm not a bodybuilder. I'm
interested in posture. I'm interested in
strength. And I'll I essentially do some
sort of pushing movement like a low
incline press and then some sort of fly
type movement. Although sometimes I'll
just do low incline bench press for so
couple warm-ups, two or three warm-ups,
two or three work sets
>> in the failing somewhere between five
and 12 repetitions.
>> Mhm.
>> And then dips, weighted dips. Big
believer in these. Like I think it's
like an upper body squat, whatever that
means. Weighted dips typically with a
weight vest. and it looks ridiculous,
but the chains are great if you can
throw those on cuz you can like toss one
off and then keep going if you if you
want to keep going. Whereas if you got a
weight hanging between your legs, which
always just feels weird to me anyway.
You're like waddling around the gym,
it's clanking into your ankles, I'll do
some sort of dip and then I'll do some
sort of row for the back. Typically like
a low row or a dumbbell row, one arm
dumbbell row, and then some sort of
chinning movement. Although I put the
chins first because we've all got this
thing of how many can I do? And I
recently bought a Nautilus pullover
machine based on the training with
Dorian and it's from 1976 and it's one
of only two that still exist and it's
kind of like some guys like muscle cars.
I like old school strength training
equipment.
>> Dorian loves his pullovers just like
Arthur Jones.
>> And by the way, if you're rowing heavy
and you're doing these things, you're
getting some forearm training.
>> But then I'll do the neck training and
I'll either use the four-way neck
machine. Jeff Cavalier from Athletex has
a great video on how to train with a
plate. You wrap it in a a train neck
with a plate and a bench. So you could
do that anywhere. You wrap it in a
towel. You lie on your side and you're
just you have to be careful about
closing the chain. So you you know you
got one leg down and you got a hand down
on the ground. The video describes it.
Maybe we could put a link to it. One
thing that's very important I learned
about training neck is you need to nasal
breathe the whole time. Have your tongue
on the roof of your mouth and make sure
that you're not sticking your chin out
at any point while you're bending it to
the side because then you start getting
clicking in your jaw. And my spinal
surgeon friends tell me that it's a
great way to slip a disc in your in your
neck. The neck aesthetically like people
don't It's always weird when like dudes
are talking about aesthetics like but
these days because of the looks maxing
thing and all that like it's it [snorts]
seems to be like more of but there's
something actually very important to
>> you're not hammering your cheekbones.
>> No, I'm definitely hammering [laughter]
my cheekbones.
>> Come on, Andrew.
>> Nope. Not hammering my cheekbones. I
mean, you know, that is such a wild
thing. Yeah. No, no, no, no. But there
is something interesting. So from a
strength and stability standpoint,
training one's neck is really important
because it's the upper spine. And it I
do think it's one of the reasons I've
never had any shoulder issues. And I've
got long arms and everything points to
the fact that I should have rotator cuff
issues. I don't do any direct rotator
cuff work. I think it's because I
started training my neck a long time
ago. And aesthetically, like you have
this, this is a great opportunity to
point out just how uh perfectly
constructed you are, Tim Ferrris. you
train your neck really if you look a
head-on at a male face. If the neck sort
of arrives right at the sort of like
outer right more or less right, you
know, plus or minus a few whatever
millimeters and more or less at the
outer jaw, the outermost point of the
jaw below the ears like touching there,
you'll notice like it looks kind of
right.
>> When somebody is really wide and their
neck is not at that point, it looks like
the wrong head was placed on a body.
Then you see Lar Hamilton and you
realize like this dude just has a a
really big neck but it's appropriate for
his for his body structure and then
after the neck. So I'll do I don't know
three sets or two work sets per side.
Although you don't train neck the same
way like to like four streps and all
that. And then I'll do some core work.
And the core work that I'm a big fan of
because you also get some forearm work
in is I'll hang from a bar and I'll do
some lsits.
>> And if I've been doing them a lot lately
I'll do some pikes. Five sets of five
piking your ankles up to your hands and
then slow on the descent and then into
an LSIT if I can and I'll do maybe three
or five sets depending and then lower
back work and I have a 45°ree angle
hyperextension and I'm not taking that
to failure. The low back thing is really
important. I found that and there are a
lot of data out there that if you can
strengthen the spinal erectors your
posture is better, you're more injury
resistant but that whole workout takes
an hour tops.
>> Mhm. The next day is the high-intensity
cardio day, just max heart rate. These
days I get get on an aerodyine bike and
I would say for this for people it's
whatever you can do without getting
hurt.
>> So question for you on the aerodyine or
I guess probably assault bike.
>> This is a digression so I won't indulge
this too far but to figure out why the
assault bike worked and caught on where
the aerodyine did not. Right? You can
look at footage from Dan Gable,
legendary wrestler, working out on an
Aerodyine, but it never really spread
until the assault bike, reformatted it,
improved it in some ways. My question
for you on that real quick for people
who don't know,
>> you're using your arms on these sort of
isolateral movable handles that power
this fan. So, you can pedal and use your
arms,
>> one or the other or both. And I find
that my upper body fatigues a lot faster
than my lower body if I'm trying to do,
let's say, like a Norwegian 4x4 or
something like that, like 4 minutes on,
3 minutes off, or 4 minutes on, 4
minutes off.
>> Do you find that not to be the case for
yourself, or how do you approach it? Cuz
I've wanted to use the assault bike.
It's now easier to find an assault bike
in say a hotel gym for me than a
stationary bike that fits well
otherwise. How do you approach that?
Well, the naming piece is interesting
and maybe we get into this at some point
deeper in the discussion, but naming is
very important and it's not just
important in health and fitness and this
kind of thing. It's it's actually very
important in science and I'm a you know
a student of science as a field, not
just the field of neuroscience in terms
of the facts, but also you look at the
culture of a scientific field oftent
times the naming is what carries a field
forward very quickly and you go how can
that be? Aren't these scientists?
Shouldn't they just be focused on the
data? Nomenclature is important because
if more people are doing something
because they can talk about it to more
people using the same language, it tends
to accelerate a field. Sure.
>> Um, also assault bike sounds cool.
Stationary bike feels like you're just
pedaling. The assault bike is
interesting because I also I get like a
lot of lat work from it. Keep in mind
the day before I trained my chest and
back.
>> No, exactly. That's why I'm asking. So,
it ends up being a second kind of
stimulus, not a hypertrophy workout, but
you you sort of end up feeling like
almost like a a pump type thing
>> if you do it right.
>> I can't do more than 30 seconds on, 30
seconds off without experiencing what
you experience it, which is that my legs
just have all this gas and my arms, they
can just keep going. It all transfers to
the upper body. So, Norwegian 4x4
>> on on the assault bike just sounds like
torture to me. This workout, if I can,
I'll get outside and sprint.
>> Mhm. And you could do it on a rower, you
could sprint. You know, I think it's
just important because it's a near
allout or allout workout. 30 seconds on,
30 seconds off. Or maybe you jog a
couple laps and then you do a couple,
you know, you do a 400 on the track and
then walk a lap and then do a 400.
Whatever you do for this workout, you
know, you can come up with any number of
different variations. It's got to be
something where you can apply max effort
and not get hurt.
>> Yeah.
>> And then the next day is a shoulders,
arms. You do some sort of pressing. I'm
not big on lateral raises.
>> Some sort of press for the shoulders,
you know, couple work sets of bicep
curls, couple incline curls, some hammer
curls, overhead tricep extension for the
long head, couple work sets, some bench
dips, and there you go. Like bench dips
again. So now you're getting a little
bit of
>> other stuff working even though it's not
a allout chest and back workout. And
then the next day, which is typically on
a Sunday, I'll do some long slow
movement, ideally outside. Maybe it's a
walk in a hike with my girlfriend. Maybe
it's I'm rucking and listening to a
podcast if I'm alone. Maybe I'm jogging
in the sand. Like it could be a long
bike ride. Just something like there's
something so nice just starting the
week.
>> Jogging in the sand sounds miserable for
long.
>> Slow. It's a slow plot. You're a mule. I
like to think of like you're kind of a
mule or I'm a mule.
>> That's going to be my clip for the
teaser
>> with [laughter] a mule.
>> I'm a mule. No, I'm kidding. Cool. No,
that works. That works. That works for
me. And you know the real hard part
about that workout is not going faster.
>> Yeah. It's pretty easy to jog and then
walk. Jog and then walk. It's probably
beneficial. Yeah.
>> But that workout is as much for the
mental stimulation, but it's also
there's something so nice about going
into the work week.
>> Maybe it lands on a Monday. I don't
know. But typically for me, it lands on
a Sunday because there's something so
nice about going to the work week,
having spent as much time as possible
moving outdoors the day before. But I do
this and it ends up being six workouts a
week, but some are very, very short.
None of the resistance training stuff is
terribly long. when you're done in an
hour or so unless you're waiting for
equipment and you know at 50 I'm
continuing to you know get stronger. I'm
not you know outrageously so and it just
works. It just works and it's worked for
everyone that I know. Now one key thing
and a lot of people will what I call
they'll kind of geek this and they won't
do compound movements. You can't do
lateral raises and and I do some rear
delt flies on the whatever one or the
either chest and back day or the
shoulders and arms day. You need that
for shoulder posturally, aesthetically,
etc. But people will think, "Oh, I can
do leg extensions, leg curls to failure
once a week." No, you're also hack
squatting and belt squatting or hat
squatting and front squatting to failure
for a couple sets.
>> That's intense. You need to do the
compound movements. There's no world
where you can just, you know, do
isolation movements this way. And that's
the thing that sometimes gets forgotten
in the Yates style training. He was
doing a lot of compound movements and
he's still a proponent of that.